<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A true relation of a wonderfull sea fight betweene two great and well appointed Spanish ships or men of warre. And a small and not very well prouided English ship, who was constrained to enter into this conflict at the iland of Dominico in her passage to Virginia, as shee was determined to take in fresh water there.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1621</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 27 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 11 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A11831</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 22130</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S110896</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99846353</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99846353</idno>
            <idno type="VID">11315</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A11831)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 11315)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 937:7)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A true relation of a wonderfull sea fight betweene two great and well appointed Spanish ships or men of warre. And a small and not very well prouided English ship, who was constrained to enter into this conflict at the iland of Dominico in her passage to Virginia, as shee was determined to take in fresh water there.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[22] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by Edward Allde] for N. B[utter],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1621.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>With a title-page woodcut.</note>
                  <note>Printer's and publisher's names from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-C⁴ (-A1).</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: A sea fight.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Naval battles --  Dominica --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Anne Simpson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Anne Simpson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:11315:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:11315:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A TRVE RELATION OF OF A WONDERFVLL Sea Fight betweene two great <hi>and well appointed Spaniſh ſhips or Men of Warre.</hi> AND A ſmall and not very well prouided Engliſh Ship, who was conſtrained to enter into this conflict at the Iland of <hi>Dominico</hi> in her paſſage to <hi>Virginia,</hi> as ſhee was determined to take in freſh water there.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>woodcut of ship called the Blacke hodge</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>The <hi>Margaret</hi> and <hi>Iohn,</hi> or the <hi>Blacke Hodge.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>London Printed for <hi>N.B.</hi> 1621.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="illustration">
            <pb facs="tcp:11315:2"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>woodcut of coat of arms containing a ship and a lion passant guardant</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:11315:2"/>
            <head>A SEA FIGHT.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Auing taken our iourney to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward <hi>Virginia</hi> in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of <hi>February</hi> laſt paſt in a ſhip called the blacke <hi>Hodge,</hi> her burthen 160. tun mann'd only with 8. Iron peeces and a poore Faulcon, we ſoone ouer paſſed both the tedious endurances and fearefull dangers of ſuch a voyage, and came at laſt by the 14. of <hi>March</hi> vnder 13. and halfe Latitude, within 20 leagues of <hi>Matalina</hi> by 6. of clocke in the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, the weather ſomwhat thicke, &amp; the wind affording a reaſonable gale, whereby we deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a ſhip lying at hull, as if ſhe were careleſſe either to go backward, or forward; which cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed vs to edge with her, as deſirous to know what ſhe was: but ſhe preſently ſet vp all her ſayles, and taking a courſe of South and by Weſt ran quickly out of ſight in the ſpace of three or foure glaſſes: this made vs keepe our courſe for <hi>Matalina,</hi> which we attained by the nex day at night, being the 15. of <hi>March,</hi> and ſo waſting the Iland of <hi>Dominico,</hi> wee bare with <hi>Guardalupo,</hi> and there anchored to take in freſh water which we wanted.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:11315:3"/>
            <p>Then came aboord vs certaine <hi>Indians,</hi> and 6. <hi>Frenchmen,</hi> who had remained there ſome 16. moneths, being caſt vpon the land by ſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wracke, and ſo were vnprouided for a further iourney: they enformed vs of a <hi>Spaniſh</hi> man of warre that paſt along ſome ſeuen dayes before diſcharging her ordinance at the inhabitants, and putting the Iland in great feare, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding ſome two dayes before there ancho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red another ſhip, whoſe Captaine with ſome ſouldiers came a ſhore with wine and other prouiſion, as if they meant to make merry and ſhew all the ſignes of friendſhip and content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: but ſhe ſtayd but one night at anchor, and ſo departed without further notice; what courſe ſhe meant to take, nor could the inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants gueſſe, by reaſon their feare enforced their flight, into the mountaines, leſt they ſhould bee ſurpriſed: onely wee were ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertiſed by certaine <hi>Indians,</hi> that they deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined for S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Vincents,</hi> leauing word, that whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the great Fleete paſſed along they ſhould en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme the Generall, that Captaine <hi>Bartholo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mew</hi> was gone vp in proſecution of his dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions.</p>
            <p>This was the ſhip we deſcryed at Hull and ſo reſolued ſhee muſt needes bee ſome <hi>Spaniſh</hi> man of warre, becauſe no Marchant, or ſhip of burthen would loſe the aduantage of ſo fayre a
<pb facs="tcp:11315:3"/> winde to tranſport her to any port of trafficke and ſpend the time in hulling, as if ſhe lay of purpoſe to diſcouer ſome priſe, and take the aduantage of ſuch paſſengers as were to go to <hi>Menis,</hi> being the common trade way both for <hi>Engliſh</hi> and <hi>Dutch,</hi> and ſo as it appeared after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward ſhe ſtirred that courſe of purpoſe, both to deceiue the Ilanders, &amp; to betray vs, whom they had deſcryed a farre off.</p>
            <p>From <hi>Guardalupa</hi> wee departed the 18. of <hi>March</hi> haſting to <hi>Menis,</hi> and ſuſpecting the worſt, held a loofe a halfe road to be the more free fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> by reaſon we determined to repaire our ſhip, &amp; refreſh our ſelues at <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis:</hi> The ſhip being much beaten with a dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous ſtorme ſome 70. leagues from our owne coaſt, the people much diſtempered as hauing bene a 11. weeks impriſoned in an ill conditio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned ſhip, and peraduenture wanting many ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſaries, which commonly we prepare for long voyages.</p>
            <p>But ſuch was the pleaſure of God, that wee were preuented and diſappointed in theſe pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes, for falling with <hi>Menis</hi> by the 20. of <hi>March,</hi> and compaſſing the furtheſt point to ſtand in the handſommer with the ſhore, wee perceiued two tall ſhips at anchor right ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>againſt the watring place with their top ſayles looſe, and their boates going a ſhore for their men. At firſt we ſuppoſed them <hi>Hollanders,</hi> in
<pb facs="tcp:11315:4"/> reſpect of their building, and the <hi>Hollanders</hi> co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ours borne by their Admirall in the mayne top, the vice Admirall hauing his fore-top ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> downe, and no colours diſplayed, which encreaſed our former opinion, adding withall that i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> muſt needs bee priſe or ſome other ſhip ſub<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t to the misfortune of a fight.</p>
            <p>But driuen by neceſſity of water, and wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to refreſh our ſelues a ſhore, we trimmed our ſhip, and came to anchor fayrely by them, ſending our boate in friendly manner to hale them both vnprouided and vnarmed, which returned with certificate, that they were <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niards,</hi> wherein not fully ſatisfied by reaſon of our former apprehenſion that it was otherwiſe the better to be reſolued, we ſent out our boat againe, as well to be aſſured what to truſt vnto as to gaine ſometime to prepare our ſhip, and trim her more commodiouſly, being peſtered with goods and fardels betweene the deckes and altogether vnprouided for any fight ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther offenſiue or defenſiue.</p>
            <p>The boate approched the hindmoſt ſhip, which I call the vice-Admirall, and haled her, demanding who they were, but in ſteed of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoluing vs, ſhee commanded them to come a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boord, and would anſwer no otherwiſe, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon the boat rowed from them, as reſoluing all was not well, and ſo made haſte vnto vs a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, yet could not preuent a volley of ſmall
<pb facs="tcp:11315:4"/> ſhot powred very dangerouſly amongſt them, inſomuch that they had their cloathes ſhot through, their oares ſhiuered, and the ſides battered with bullets: yet thankes bee to God neither was a man hurt, nor any thing loſt, which, as if they had had notice of the ſame e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcape, rated their rage ſo much the more. For by that time the boat was out of reach of their ſmall ſhot, they followed it to the ſhip with great Ordnance, and when they per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued they were ſafely come aboord, they tooke it ſo ill, that they thundred againſt our ſhip with the ſoarer rage, and moſt violent vol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyes, which wee could not anſwer, hauing no peece in our gunner roome, nor indeed any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther well mounted for ſuch a Sea fight.</p>
            <p>By this time we vnderſtood what they were, and reſolued wee ſhould not depart quietly without miſchiefe, whereupon our Maſter ſet vs on worke to haue brought our Ordnance into frame, and ſo to order our ſhip that wee might defend our ſelues if need were, but ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny things failing vs, we practiſed to weigh our anchors, which was not to be done ſo ſodain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, confidering our encombrances on ſhip boord: we then reſolud to weigh it vp with the boat, had not ſo many ſhot thundred amongſt vs, that we wondred at our eſcape.</p>
            <p>By this time their vice Admirall heaued vp her anchor to her warpe, and laid her ſelfe to
<pb facs="tcp:11315:5"/> wind-ward, if either wee ſhould paſſe forward, or anchor ſhort againe, ſo that wee perceiued they meant to aſſault vs on all hands: for ſhee let flie a whole broad ſide vpon vs, and came furiouſly vp to our lee quarter without da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage or reſiſtance of our parts, to which ſure they were the rather induced becauſe the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirall hauing receiued her men from ſhore, her top ſayle looſe all ready, and many things commodious to their purpoſe, began to weigh anchor, and made toward vs amaine.</p>
            <p>But when we were thus terrified and threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by them, and thus encombred and diſani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mated amongſt our ſelues, knowing withall (by reaſon of our ill prepared Ordnance) the diſaduantage and hazard to be boorded at an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chor by two good ſhips well prepared for ſpoyle and ruine, we hoyſed vp our ſayles, and determined to ſet forward, had not the vice-Admirall come on our ſtar-boord ſide, and beat vpon vs ſo hardly, that we fell to our bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſſe, and anſwered their vnkindneſſe accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly with many faire ſhot, which prooued moſt effectuall, eſpecially from a demy culue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, which at laſt ſhot her betweene winde &amp; water, ſo that ſhe was compelled from vs, and bare off to Sea, leauing her Admirall onely ſingle with vs, who at laſt came fairely in our quarter to wind-ward, taking in her <hi>Holland</hi> flag, and aduanced her <hi>Spaniſh</hi> colours, and ſo
<pb facs="tcp:11315:5"/> haled vs.</p>
            <p>Wee quietly and quickly anſwered, both what we were, and whither we were bound, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcouering the effect of our commiſſion, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lating the cauſe of our tarying there for water, neither purpoſing to annoy any ſubiect of the king of <hi>Spains,</hi> nor by way of affront to braue either Marchant or man of Warre. Then ſhe charged vs to ſtrike our ſailes for the king of <hi>Spaine,</hi> and vaile the bonnet according to the prerogatiue they had in thoſe Seas: we replyed with enlarging the particulars of the league betweene the King our Maſter and their king, adding withall, that as we intended no ill, wee would take no wrong, whereupon the Maſter left the poope, and ſequeſtred himſelfe from ſuch open conference; had they not called for the Captaine againe, who at laſt preſented himſelfe, till they commanded him to come aboord with his commiſſion, which he refuſed yet wiſhed them to ſend their boat aboord, &amp; then they ſhould ſee it moſt willingly.</p>
            <p>But inſtead either of anſwering vs further with kind words, or accepting of our reply in good part, they made two great ſhot at vs, and poured among vs ſuch a volley of ſmall ſhot, before wee could get off the poope, that wee thanked God they did no more harme, yet we were much amazed they did ſo much: not thus content they waued vs mith their bright
<pb facs="tcp:11315:6"/> ſword<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, an reuiled vs with opprob<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ious tearms miſ-<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>earming vs dogs, and inuenting more o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious names againſt vs then we could imagin, that Chriſtians durſt vrge one another withal: at laſt they layd vs aboord, which enforced vs to raiſe vp our maine ſaile, and to giue the word to our ſmall ſhot, which all this while lay cloſe well reſolued and prepared: but ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dainly breaking foorth we plyed them in ſuch ſort that we made them giue backe &amp; ſhrinke from their former forwardneſſe.</p>
            <p>The fight continued ſome halfe houre in our quarter, and according to the terror of ſuch encounters, we were compaſt as it were in fire and ſmoake, vntill they diſcouered the waſt of our ſhip naked, and were encouraged with the hope of reciprocall damage, whereupon they brauely ran vpon our ſide, and layd vs aboord lufe to lufe, haſtning with pikes and ſwords to enter, to which was added ſuch fury, that if they had not beene preuented, we ſhould haue ſhrunke vnder the rage of a barbarous ſlaugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: but it pleaſed God ſo to direct our Maſter with aduice, and encourage our men with va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour, that our pikes being formerly placed vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der our halfe decke, and certaine ſhot lying cloſe for that purpoſe vnder the portels of the ſhip, encountred them ſo brauely, that their fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry was not onely rebated, but their haſtineſſe intercepted, and the whole company beaten
<pb facs="tcp:11315:6"/> backe, eſpecially vpon the wind-ward ſide, where the charge was hotteſt, and the fight bloodieſt; for there the throng was great, and men had worke enough to make proofe of their courages &amp; fortunes, diuers of our men were hurt, and many fell on their ſide; if a man retired wounded with vs, two I am ſure were ſlaine amongſt them; if their pikes reached as farre as our bodyes, ours were long enough to faſten in their ſides; if a Partiſon fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> gaſhed our armes, a Halbard from vs lighted on their heads: yea, we came ſo neere, that ſwords cut pikes a ſunder, and targets were hewed with the blowes, ſo that if a fight were woorth the deſcribing: it is pitty that ſome great Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manders on both ſides beheld not this, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord the action to memory, and recompence the men with ſufficient reward.</p>
            <p>In the end they were violently repulſed by vs, enforced to a retreat, vntill they were rein<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forced backe againe by their Commanders, who ſtanding vpon tearmes of honour, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing men of warre, and deſigned for that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, thought it an indignity to be ſo afronted and countermaunded, which cauſed a ſecond charge, and that was anſwered with a ſecond beating backe, till the Captaine himſelfe grew enraged, as not brooking to bee ſo much ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mated, and conſtrained them to come on a freſh, which they did ſo effectually, that que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtionleſſe
<pb facs="tcp:11315:7"/> it had wrought an alteration, if the God that toſſeth Monarchies, and teareth the Mountaines in his fury, had not taught vs to toſſe our pikes with proſperous euent, and poured out a ſodaine volley of ſmall ſhot vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them, whereby that worthy Commander was ſlaine at the foote of a pike and many of his ſouldiers dropped down on the top of the hatches.</p>
            <p>This we ſaw with our eyes, and reioyced at with our hearts, ſo that we might perceiue as it were good ſucceſſe comming on, &amp; deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance to breake through the thicking cloud of that vengeance which was prepared againſt vs: for preſently our Maſter tooke aduantage of their diſcomfiture (though with ſome commi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeration for that valiant Captaine ſo ſlaine) that he not only plyed them a freſh with great ordinance, but had more falſe ſhot vnder the pikes, which were beſtowed to good purpoſe, &amp; amaſed our enemies with the ſodainneſſe.</p>
            <p>Amongſt the reſt one <hi>Lucas</hi> our Carpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters mate muſt not be forgotte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, who perceiued a way how to annoy them, as they were thus puſled and in a confuſion, drue out a minion which hee nobly ſet a worke vnder the halfe decke, till at the laſt he brought it to the doxe of the halfe decke, and there bent it vpon them but in ſuch a manner, that when it was fiered the caſes full of ſtones and peeces of Iron fell
<pb facs="tcp:11315:7"/> vpon them like haile, and cleared their decke in ſuch a ſort that it ſlue many, and in ſhort time we ſaw few aſſailants, but onely ſuch as crept from place to place very couertly, and ſeemed willing to obſcure themſelues from the fury of our ſhot, which now was thicker then theirs. For although (as farre as wee may commend our enemies) they had done ſome things wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of admiration: yet either wanting men, or ouertaken with the vnlooked for valour of our company, they now began to ſhrinke, and gaue vs leaue to be wanton with our aduantage.</p>
            <p>Yet were our great Ordnance onely foure that wee could vſe in this fight, but it ſhould ſeeme they ſerued the turne as well as foure times foure: for they ſhot her diuers times be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene winde and water, and ſo preuailed, that at laſt we ſaw many ſignes of their willingnes to leaue vs, but by reaſon ſhe was faſt in a ſlach of our cable, which in haſt of weighing our anchor hung looſe, ſhe could not be diuided nor make that way ſhe purpoſed, vntill one of our men cut it with an axe without direction, and was ſlaine for his labour. But when ſhee perceiued ſhe was looſe, after ſhe had beene a boord two houres and a halfe, good Lord what haſt ſhe made, and how quickly were we diuided, both great and ſmall ſhot playing on both ſides, which laſted vntill the remoteneſſe was aboue a Caliuer ſhot, and we diſcouered
<pb facs="tcp:11315:8"/> the vice Admirall comming to her aſſiſtance, who began a farre off to ply vs with great ſhot and put vs in mind, wee had another worke in hand.</p>
            <p>Whereupon wee manned our ſhip a new, ſeparating the dead and hurt bodies by them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues from vs, and were ſo encouraged, that we waued her, and in a manner made toward her to fight a freſh. For whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we perceiued, that the Admirall made not a ſhot more at vs, wee verily imagined, that either ſhe was preparing her ſelfe with a new ſupply, or wanted men to make her ſeruiceable, or reſolued to goe away from vs, conſidering ſhe had loſt her Captain; yet loth to be ſecure, and imagining the vice Admirall might come and boord vs finding vs play, till the Admirall did make her ſelfe better ready, wee prepared our ſelues, wondring yet that ſhe came no neerer vs then Falcon ſhot, wherewith ſhe plyed vs ſtill on the lee fide, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till at laſt ſhe receiued another payment from our demy Culuering, which ſhot her through, &amp; made her beare with the ſhore into ſmooth water, where ſhe remained till 2. of the clocke after midnight, and ſo we had time to reforme our diſorders, and make our ſelues better rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy for the next dayes varietie.</p>
            <p>By breake of day ſhee came vp againe with the Admirall with her; as if they determined indeed to deuoure vs at once; but as it ſeemed
<pb facs="tcp:11315:8"/> it was but a Brauado, though for the time they forſooke not our quarter within Musket ſhot: for all that night and morning they were qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et neighbours, and kept vs company without any great anoya<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce with their top ſailes down, not knowing, as it ſhould ſeeme, what to doe with vs, or elſe ſuſpecting their owne hurts and leakes, they durſt not truſt themſelues too far from land, nor to the fury of another encoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</p>
            <p>All that night wee had time and leyſure to ouerlooke our loſſes, and prepare for them if they aſſayled vs againe; and indeed wee were better prouided then before, &amp; better accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modated in our ſhip, as freeing it from former encombrances, &amp; affoording farre more ſcope for our Ordnance to play vpon them: but God be thanked it fell out otherwiſe: for though we might perceiue them ſpeake together, and with many yards a croſſe entend to keepe vs company; yet did they not make much haſt vp, nor trouble vs with many ſhot, till the next day the Admirall made ſhew of an encounter, and we after prayers were ended prouided to fight with them, but ſodainely wee perceiued the vice Admirall hang a ſterne, cutting her maine ſayle to come vp, and ſtirring very ill, which aſtoniſhed vs the more, becauſe wee could not imagine the reaſon, conſidering ſhe was the beſt ſayler and now ſpared her Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall
<pb facs="tcp:11315:9"/> a fore-top ſayle, ſhewing all the ſignes of retracting, and no deſire to come too neere vs any more.</p>
            <p>At length the Admirall ſhooke in the wind and by apparant ſignes gaue vs notice of ſlack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing her courſe, whereby we might run a head and follow the ſeas at our pleaſure, ſo we per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued the vice Admirall with all her ſailes to make towards an Iland called <hi>Sana,</hi> which the Admirall either tooke notice of, as knowing the danger ſhe was in, or gaue directions ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly, conſidering there was no good to be done with vs: for preſently ſhe tacked about and loſt vs, bearing toward that Iland alſo, which wee eaſily diſcouered with her whole length: but the ſhips were quickly out of ſight, although wee ſaw the breach of the ſheare all along, and how the Admirall departed from vs, which cauſed vs to imagine, that ſhee was forced a ſhore by her leakes receiued in the fight, and durſt not aduenture for feare ſhee ſhould haue beene ſuncke altogether, &amp; que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtionleſſe the Admirall had neuer gone from our ſides, nor tryed any fortune but our cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſie, if we could by any meanes haue brought ouer our demy Culuering on our fighting ſide which was endeuoured by our Maſter &amp; Gun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner: but as you haue heard our ſhip being ſo encombred, it was in vaine, and we little drea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, either of Pirats or aduerſary in thoſe
<pb facs="tcp:11315:9"/> ſeas, made leſſe account to bee intercepted in this manner: but ſuch is the condition of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine life, that commonly miſchiefes come vnlooked for, and when they come, accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny one another with much variety, eſpecially at Sea, where I will bee bold to ſay, that a fight is more terrible to frailty, and yeeldeth greater occaſion of aſtoniſhment, then a maine battle at land, or the ſurpriſing of a towne in the fury of an execution.</p>
            <p>This fight continued fiue or ſixe houres, &amp; was the more vnwelcome, becauſe we were ſo vnprouided, and had no intents, nor gaue any occaſion to diſturbe them, as for the loſſe of men, and accidentall troubles if religion had not taught vs, what by Gods prouidence is brought to paſſe; yet morality and dayly expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience might enforme vs of the dangers of warre, and perils at Sea, by ſtorms, tempeſts, ſhipwrackes, encountring with Pirats, mee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting with enemies, croſſe winds, long voyages, vnkown ſhores, barbarous nations, deuouring monſters, and a hundred inconueniences, of which humane policies are not capable, nor mens coniectures apprehenſiue.</p>
            <p>We loſt Doctor <hi>Bohune,</hi> and ſeuen other were ſlaine out right: two died ſhortly after of their wounds, and 16. were ſhot through in ſome part or other of the body, whoſe wounds Gods be thanked were recured and without
<pb facs="tcp:11315:10"/> maime or further impeachment of health are now recouered and ſetled in <hi>Virginia,</hi> accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to our firſt entended purpoſe and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion: I reckon not ſuch as are hurt with pikes and other offenſiue weapons, becauſe there was no danger in their cures, and the skilfull Surgeon ſhewed his art &amp; good ſpeed with facility. How many they loſt we ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not tel, nor what men of name were entertained a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them, onely I am ſure we ſaw many lye ſlaine on the decke, and more caſt ouer boord in the fight, beſides the ſcuppers ran with blood, and the very Sea in their quarter was coloured with a Scarlet hue, and looked fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully vpon vs all.</p>
            <p>O the ambition and turbulency of mens na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and the ill condition of reuenge, that cannot bee contented with faire ſatisfaction, vnleſſe it be anſwered with death and blood: I ſpeake not of the vniuſtifiable proceedings of Pirates, becauſe the diuell hath any ſcuſe fo ſuch theft, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the neceſſity of life &amp; the terror of pouerty, which ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not be preuented in great and ſturring ſpirits without courſe of actiue imployment, or ſome endeauours or other: but of the inſatiate pride of the heart, and the wicked diſpoſition of mallice, which is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſatisfied, but with the death and deſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of an enemy, as was apparant in this encoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. For we could not imagin, why they ſhould
<pb facs="tcp:11315:10"/> aduenture thus vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs, vnleſſe to make vs priſe, and ſubiect to the ſpoyle of robbery. As for the pretence of their kings prerogatiue, there was not ſo much as a thought of afronting the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in that kinde, had they not inſulted as it were ouer vs in an ouerdaring manner, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded vs to that which we knew was diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable to our nation and diſgratious to our ſelues: but for feare of lauiſhes and burſtings out of frailty, I will now deſiſt, either from complayning of them, or exſcuſing our ſelues; &amp; only conclude, there were ſome hreat faults co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted amongſt vs all on both ſides, which the God of heauen determined to puniſh in this manner, and that God of heauen direct vs to make vſe of his iudgements, that we not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly pray to him for the diuerſion of his wrath from our ſinnes, but yeeld him all poſſible praiſe and thankſgiuing for any deliuerance, or bleſſing whatſoeuer, and more particularly for this our vnlookt for eſcape from ſo great a danger.</p>
            <p>The buhthen of their Admirall was 300. tuns, hauing 22. peeces of Braſſe, and all pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſion of a man of Warre indeed: their Vice-Admirall 300. tuns, and 16. caſt peeces, nor much inferior to her for trimming and corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpondent equipage, and both to the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward ſhew ouer-maſterfull and daring for one poore Marchant and paſſenger, being but a
<pb facs="tcp:11315:11"/> 160. tuns, hauing 8. Iron peeces and one Fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>con, ouerloaden with ſtuffe and wares, encom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred with paſſengers, toyled with a ſtorme, ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with a long voyage, affrighted with wants, and euery way inſufficient to anſwer any ſuch enemy: but as it in the Scripture, it is all one to thee O God, whether there bee few or many, and <hi>Gedeons</hi> 300. ſhall ſlay many thouſands of the <hi>Midianites:</hi> as for deliuerances, the people of <hi>Iſrael</hi> ſhall paſſe through the red Sea dry foot: <hi>Ionas</hi> ſhall be caſt ſafe on ſhore out of the Whales belly: and <hi>Paul</hi> ſhal eſcape ſhipwrack, ſauing his life with all his paſſengers in the I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land of <hi>Malia.</hi> For to conclude with the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe in hand, there is one thing moſt remarke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able as an inducement to this our deliuerance, that Captaine <hi>Cheſter</hi> embraced Doctor <hi>Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hune</hi> being mortally wounded, &amp; thus recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forted him, ſaying, O Doctor <hi>Bohune</hi> what a diſaſter is this; the noble Doctor no whit exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimated, replyed; Fight it out braue man, the cauſe is good, and Lord receiue my ſoule.</p>
            <div type="lists_of_casualties">
               <list>
                  <pb facs="tcp:11315:11"/>
                  <head>Slaine out-right.</head>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Doctor Bohune.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Thomas Demeter Gent.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Th. Read.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>William Garret.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Th. Vernam.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Gabriel Peies.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Dauid Bathering,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Raph. &amp;c.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>Died after.</head>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Francis Annis Gent.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Ed. Nerobery ſayler.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>Wounded yet cured.</head>
                  <item>
                     <hi>William Bird. Gent.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Alexander Bouentine.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>William Bannington Gent.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Will. Ioyce quarter</hi> M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Iohn wakings.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Iohn Wilſon Sayler.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>George Tayler Sayler.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>William Lucas Sayler.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Iohn Robbins Steward.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Phillip Durwine.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Three French men.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Robert Lector.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Anthony Browne Gent.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
